Finding Aid for Redford Presbyterian Church records, 1906-2009
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Redford Avenue Presbyterian Church records 1906-2009
Redford Avenue Presbyterian Church (Detroit, Mich.)
1 oversize items
3 oversize volumes
13 linear feet (in 16 boxes)
2009150 Ba 2
Detroit, Michigan Presbyterian Church; organizational records, publications, baptismal and membership records, scrapbooks, files of the women’s organization.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records of the church (donor no. 3245 ) came to the library in July 2009.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Redford Avenue Presbyterian Church was established in March 1906 by a small congregation that served what was then known as Sand Hill in Detroit. Four men, Allen M. Bosworth, Dr. Samuel J. Holcomb, David N. Reid and William J. Stringer made up a committee to place the request before the Detroit Presbytery. They were advised that meetings should be held, with the congregation to be organized later. A meeting was held in the Masonic hall and these four men were named as a finance committee. About $2500 was raised and Mr. and Mrs. Allen Bosworth gave three lots to be used as a church site. Construction began and the cornerstone was laid on August 20, 1905. The first church building was dedicated on December 31st, 1905.
On February 2nd, 1906, the articles of incorporation were signed by the four men of the original committee along with Emery Becker, F. L. DeNio, Chas. A. Lahser, John M. Paulger, Chas. H. Philbrick, Eugene Smith, L. N. Tupper and Alonzo P. Woodruff. On March 4th, 1906 the church was accepted by the Presbytery and organized with thirty-nine charter members. It was served by supply ministers until October 22nd, 1906, when the Rev. J. Archie McKee of East Jordan was called as minister.
The church was known as the First Presbyterian Church of Redford until 1926, when the name was changed to Redford Avenue Presbyterian Church. The church's membership grew rapidly, and as a result, in 1929, a separate addition was built to accommodate the larger congregation. Unfortunately, in 1945 the sanctuary was completely destroyed by a fire. However, this tragedy provided an important opportunity for the congregation and community to work together to rebuild the church, and by 1954, a new sanctuary, educational wing and fellowship hall was constructed. By the late 1960s, the membership had grown to more than 3,600 people. Beginning in the 1970s, membership would begin to decline. Eventually, in 2009, with fewer members to pay the bills and with the expense of maintaining their aging facility, the membership voted to consolidate with Southfield Presbyterian Church.
The records have been arranged into the following series: Administrative and Topical Files; Board of Deacons, Reports and Directories; Women's Organizations; Schooner Mariners; Publications; Baptismal Records; Membership Records; and Scrapbooks.
Subjects:
Detroit (Mich.)--Church history.; Presbyterian Church--Michigan--Detroit.; Redford Avenue Presbyterian Church (Detroit, Mich.); Redford (Detroit, Mich.)--Church history.; Registers of births, etc.--Michigan--Detroit.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Scrapbooks.
- Administrative and Topical Files
  - History and Background Information (Box 1)
  - Anniversaries
    - 50th anniversary 1955 (Box 1)
    - 75th anniversary 1981 (Box 1)
    - 100th anniversary 2006 (Box 1)
  - Church building
    - Architect's drawings for new building (not accepted) (Box 1)
    - Minutes of Planning Committee, Architect's Committee, Furnishings Committee for new additions 1957-1960 (Box 1)
  - Commission on Christian Education 1957-1962 (Box 1)
  - Congregational and Corporation By-Laws (Box 1)
  - Cornerstone laying 1954 (Box 1)
  - Demographic survey (area profile) 1994 (Box 1)
  - Demographic charts 1967 (Box 16)
    (see also oversize chart)
  - Homecoming Celebration 1987-2004 (Box 1)
  - Kinderkirk (Box 1)
  - Merger proposal 1994 (Box 1)
  - Pastoral Nominating Committee: Call of Calvin W. Didier 1964 (Box 1)
  - Program Committee and Related (Box 1)
  - Riddering (Albert A.) Tribute (Box 1)
  - Strategic Planning Task Force and related 1989-1993 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Photographs of church social events, 2 volumes; 1 folders (Box 1)
- Board of Deacons
  - Minutes of meetings 1952-1980, 1997, 1999, 9 folders (Box 2)
  - Secretary's record books containing combination of minutes of deacons, trustees, and annual meetings
    - 1963-1966 (Box 2)
    - 1966-1968 (Box 2)
    - 1995-1996 (Box 2)
- Reports and Directories
  - Annual Reports 1950, 1952-2008, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Membership Directories 1964-2007 (Box 3)
    (with some gaps)
  - Yearbook 1958 of Annual Congregation -- Corporation Meeting, January 26, 1959 (Box 3)
- Women's Organizations
  - Woman's Union
    - Board minutes 1906-1943, 1 folders; 6 volumes (Box 3)
      (The Redford Woman's Association was formed in 1943)
  - Woman's Association
    - Constitution and By-Laws (Box 3)
    - Minutes
      - 1947-1948 (Box 3)
      - 1950 (Box 3)
      - 1957-1958 (Box 4)
      - 1959-1961 (Box 4)
      - 1962-1963 (Box 4)
      - 1972-1976 (Box 4)
      - 1977 (Box 4)
      - 1978 (Box 4)
      - 1981-1982 (Box 4)
      - 1982 (Box 4)
      - 1982-1983 (Box 4)
    - Annual Reports 1949-1988 (Box 4)
    - Yearbooks 1956-1995 (Box 4)
    - Budgets 1957-1970s (Box 4)
  - Presbyterian Women in the Redford Presbyterian Church (PWRPC)
    - Minutes and financial material 1997-2004 (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous: Annual reports, constitution, and yearbooks (Box 4)
  - Women's Missionary Society
    - Minute book 1921-1925 (Box 4)
    - Minute book 1925-1931 (Box 4)
    - Annual Programs 1920s-1930s (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Woman's group meetings 1922-1925 (Box 4)
    - Dorcas Society minute book 1894-1898 (Box 4)
    - Combined records: Fellowship Bible Class 1935-1942 and New Life Movement, 1949-1950 (Box 4)
    - Priscilla Circle (Box 5)
    - Women's Circles membership lists (Box 5)
    - Installation service programs (Box 5)
    - Mother-Daughter banquets, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Comic fashion show (Box 5)
    - Correspondence and miscellaneous (Box 5)
    - Photographs of church fundraiser (Box 5)
- Schooner Mariners
  - Constitution (Box 5)
  - Program flyers (Box 5)
  - Secretary's notebook (Box 5)
  - Membership lists (Box 5)
  - Minutes and related material 1992-1995 (Box 5)
  - Madrigal Feast 1995 (Box 5)
  - Boar's Head Festival (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 5)
- Publications
  - Newsletters
    - 1937-1945, 4 volumes (Box 5)
    - 1945-1948, 2 volumes (Box 6)
    - 1961, 1963-1968, 1972 (Box 6)
    - 1973-1997, 7 folders (Box 6)
  - Weekly bulletins
    - 1937-1951, 1 folders (Box 6)
    - 1957-1966, 1 folders (Box 7)
    - 1967-1973, 1 folders (Box 7)
    - 1974-1977, 1 folders (Box 7)
    - 1978-1979 (Box 8)
    - 1980 1982 (Box 8)
    - 1983, 1985-1986 (Box 8)
    - 1992-2009 (scattered dates) (Box 8)
- Baptismal records
  - 1952, 1 volumes (Box 9)
  - 1968-1969 (Box 9)
  - 1969-1974, 1 volumes (Box 9)
  - 1975-1985, 1 volumes (Box 9)
  - Stubs from baptismal records 1940s-1980s (Box 9)
- Membership records
  - Certificates of dismissions and transferals (Box 10)
  - Church treasurer account book listing names and amounts pledged and received (Box 11)
    - 1916-1919 (Box 11)
    - 1919-1924 (Volume 1)
    - 1924-1934 (Box 11)
  - Card file with name and address of members (past and to date) (Box 12)
  - Card file with name and address of members (past and to date) (Box 13)
    (continued)
  - Card file with name and address of members (past and to date) (Box 14)
- Scrapbooks
  - Women's Association
    - 1906-1942 (Box 15)
    - 1930-1965 (Box 15)
    - 1958-1981 (Box 15)
    - 1980-1992 (scattered dates) (Volume 2)
  - Schooner Mariners
    - 1954-1989 (Volume 3)
    - 1960-1976 (Box 15)